מזל טוב. Mazel Tov. Today's דף Daf is קי"א. Kuf Yud Aleph.
We pick up on the last line of ק"י עמוד ב'. Kuf
Yud Amud Bet. We're going through each of the people that inherit
from one another. We did a father inherits from his children, which
is not in the פסוקים. Psukim. We learned it out from different
פסוקים, Psukim, but let's say the דרשה Drasha
of שארו הקרוב אליו, She'ero Hakaro Elav, and שארו She'ero is the
father, and we inserted him between the children and the brother. Then
we learned out between the children, the פשט Pshat of the פסוקים.
Psukim. It took a long time to sort of underscore the פשט
Pshat of the פסוקים. Psukim. But the פשט Pshat of the פסוקים
Psukim is that first it goes to sons, if no sons then
daughters. Then we'd inserted the father,
and then we had the brothers. The brothers are explicit in the
פסוקים. Psukim. The פסוק Pasuk says, ואם אין לו בת ונתתם את
נחלתו לאחיו, Ve'im ein lo bat unetatem et nachalato le'achiv, but the
גמרא Gemara said that the point the גמרא Gemara needed to make
there was that it was a brother defined by a paternal brother
with a shared father based on the general principle that משפחת אב
קרויה משפחה משפחת אם אינה קרויה משפחה. Mishpachat Av Kriya Mishpacha, Mishpachat
Em Eina Kriya Mishpacha. Okay, so now we've got that whole thing,
right? Son, daughter, father, brother, and then father's brother. So that's basically
the whole משנה Mishna except the things that aren't in the פסוקים,
Psukim, which is, so now we're going to start with them. There's
wife and there's mother. So let's take a look. ואיש את אמו.
Ve'ish Et Imo. Yeah.
What is the word שארו She'ero really?
We mentioned that before, I think you might not have been here,
it's like flesh. Yeah.
But like how does it, like is it related to like the
וישאר? Vayisha'er?
Oh, that I don't know, that I don't know, but it's flesh.
כי אחינו בשרנו הוא, Ki achinu besarenu hu, שאר. She'er. Anyway, so
there's a whole רמב"ן Ramban about that by the פסוק Pasuk ויהיו
לבשר אחד, Vayihyu Levasar Echad, which is relevant to husband and wife
as we've discussed, and like שאר כסותה ועונתה She'er Ksuta Ve'onata and
so on. Okay, ואיש את אמו, Ve'ish Et Imo, a man inherits
from his mother. Now, the mother does not inherit from her son
as we've seen, that we said explicitly, right? Because משפחת אב קרויה
משפחה משפחת אם אינה קרויה משפחה, Mishpachat Av Kriya Mishpacha, Mishpachat Em
Eina Kriya Mishpacha, but a man inherits from his mother. מנא הני
מילי, Mena Hanei Milei, where do you know this from? Now, before
we go on, תוספות Tosafot asks like, well, I don't understand, we
already said that the inheritance goes, you know, son and then daughter
and then brother, etc. So if that's true when a man dies,
that should be true when a woman dies. So if a woman
dies, it should go to her son. What's the issue? So if
you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot makes a very
important point which fits into, of course, the general theme we've been
talking about. ואיש את אמו מנא הני מילי. Ve'ish Et Imo Mena
Hanei Milei. אמר ריב"ם, Omer Ribam,
דבשאר ירושות של נשים, Debishar Yerushot Shel Nashim, other types of inheriting,
this is means from women, not that women inherit, but inheriting from
a woman who dies, okay? כגון בתו או אחותו, Kegon Bito O
Achoto, a man's daughter were to die or his sister were to
die. פשיטא דיורשת אותה אביה או אחיה, Psita Dei'yorashet Ota Aviha O
Acheiha, it should be.
So if a woman dies, it would be obvious that her father
would inherit her or a brother would inherit her, right? We've already
established the order of inheritance. So what does it matter if it's
a woman who dies who passes on her property or a man
who dies? So the גמרא Gemara says כיון שאינה ירושה נעקרת ממשפחת
אב. Kivan She'eina Yerusha Na'akeret Mimishpachat Av. Because if a
woman dies and her husband inherits, excuse me, her father inherits from
her or her brother inherits from her, it all stays within the,
you know, patriarchal family, right?
I'm going to understand why? Because those are blood relatives through the
father.
ופשיטא שהזכר והנקבה שוים. Upsita Shehazachar Vehanekava Shavim. And it's obvious that
men and women are the same. בין לירש בין להוריש, Bein Lirash
Bein Lehorish, whether to inherit or whether to bequeath. etc. Always to
the, they don't inherit in the same way, daughters come after sons,
but anyway, but certainly when they die to pass on their property,
it's all going to be the same. So once we've got the
whole system set up, why do you need a פסוק Pasuk about
when a woman dies? So he says דמה לי זכר ומה לי
נקבה. Demali Zachar U'mali Nekava. דאטו נכסי נשים יהו הפקר? De'atu Nechasei
Nashim Yehu Hefker? I don't understand, you think because just because the
פסוקים Psukim are talking about a man dying, it means a woman
dies, it's a free for all? Okay, so obviously once we establish
what happens when somebody dies, it doesn't matter if it's a man
or it's a woman. Okay, so then why are we asking the
question when a mother dies, does her son inherit from her? It
says ודווקא בן בנכסי האם צריך למילף. Vidafka Ben Benichasei Ha'em Tsarich
Limalaf. לפי שנסבת נחלה לה ממטה אביה על ידי הבן, Lefi Shenisvet
Nachala Lah Mimateh Aviha Al Yedei Haben, right? Because when a mother
dies and her son inherits her, the property of that woman that
she got from her father's family is now going on to her
son who might very well be of a different tribe, right? A
woman that's born to the שבט הדן Shevet HaDan and she marries
a man from like שבט ראובן, Shevet Reuven, when she dies the
property she took from her family's from her father's household, right? From
the דנית נחלה, Danite Nachala, in the דנית Danite section of ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, is now going to pass on to her son
who's from ראובן, Reuven, right? You're not understanding?
That's what I was starting to think about the geographic...
Right, so it's the same thing when a woman dies, right? The
same thing, and that was the whole reason that the uncles of
the בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelafchad complained, right? Is because a woman who
passes on the who passes on the inheritance to her husband or
to her son will have the effect of taking it out of
the נחלה nachala of that tribe it originated,
exchanging the משפחת אביה mishpachat aviha and you know, so sort of
like, you know, disrupting the patriarchy as I said, the land does
not remain within the patriarchal family if it passes from a woman
and from a woman through her son or through or to her
son or to her husband. So therefore what we're going to be
looking at today is both of those, that a woman, well we
actually already spoke about a husband inheriting from his wife but we're
going to touch on it again, but but also a son or
a daughter inheriting from her mother where you have where where it
can go out of the tribal lands. So leave the משפחת בית
אביה. mishpachat beit aviha. So that's why תוספות Tosafot says of course
if a woman dies it follows all the rules that we've laid
laid out. You know, but the one thing that you need a
חידוש chidush to is that it even will transfer to somebody who
will take it out of the patriarchal household. It'll transfer to a
son, it'll transfer to a daughter, it'll transfer to a husband. If
it transfers to a blood relative of course the rules should be
the same. Okay? Yes.
For example of דן Dan and ראובן, Reuven, yeah, the effect will
be that George Rubenstein will have a house in שבט דן. Shevet
Dan. Exactly. Okay.
And the same way if she dies and her husband from ראובן
Reuven inherits her, he will have it in right.
You could go up north and all the Danites say what are
you doing?
And he says this is my נחלה. nachala.
And when יובל Yovel comes and it all restores everybody gets איש
נחלתו, ish nachalato, he retains that land because that was his נחלה
nachala that all came through.
But it doesn't go back.
It doesn't go back in the יובל. Yovel. Right, that's yeah, that's
what is so profoundly disruptive about this is that it doesn't go
back even at the time of the יובל. Yovel. This is what
he got in his נחלה. nachala. His נחלה, nachala, the נחלה nachala
of דן Dan passed down through ראובן Reuven and now דן Dan
has all these patches. Every שבט shevet will have patches of different
tribes in this.
Be a real estate lawyer. Guess all those maps we see by
a couple generations are going to be
well, it would only be in circumstances when there was no sons
and when when the person married outside of the tribe. You would
imagine most of the time a person would marry within the tribe,
right? So I mean even in today's day of like what do
you call it of of global travel and so on, I assume
most people marry people from the same state, probably a high percentage,
right?
My mother's born in Mexico.
All right fine, whatever. Moving on. Okay, מנא הני מילי, Mena hani
milei, where's this from? From Germany. Okay, מנא הני מילי. Mena hani
milei. So where is this from that when a when a man
inherits from his mother and as תוספות Tosafot says, we're even okay
with the idea that now that a woman has inherited it now
can pass out of the tribe through her child or through her
husband? So we need a פסוק pasuk to emphasize to understand that.
מנא הני מילי Mena hani milei דתנו רבנן detanu rabbanan because we
taught. Okay, וכל בת ירשת נחלה, vechol bat yoreshet nachala, any daughter
that inherits exactly a an inheritance ממטות בני ישראל. mimatot bnei Yisrael.
Like so this is when like you know what do you call
it when like משה Moshe came back when the when the uncles
complained and then משה Moshe sort of said fine they'll you know
they'll they'll marry within the tribe. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is
going to say that that was only for that generation exactly, but
that was exactly about this problem. So anyway, here's the דרשה. drasha.
היך בת ירשת שני מטות? Heich bat yoreshet shnei matot? It says
a daughter who inherits from the tribes. How can a daughter inherit
from two tribes? Okay, so you understand how she inherits from her
father's tribe, that was set up. Father dies no sons goes to
the daughter. How does she inherit from a different tribe? אלא זו
שאביה משבט אחד ואמה משבט אחר ומתו וירשתן. Ela zo she-aviha mi-shevet
echad ve-imah mi-shevet acher u-metu ve-yerashatan. Okay, she has her father from
one tribe, a mother from another, they both die, she inherits her
father and her mother. So she inherits from and there's no sons,
so she's now inherited from two tribes. ואין לי אלא בת, ve-ein
li ela bat, so now that says that a daughter can inherit
from her mother. בן מניין? Ben minayin? How do you know a
son can? Now let's just pause here, right? Why should it be
a difference? I mean sons always you know at least come before
daughters in inheritance. So obviously if a daughter should inherit a son
should inherit. So the no well that will be the answer, but
I want to just pause and appreciate the הוה אמינא hava amina
because as תוספות Tosafot points out, the effect of a woman dying
and passing it on to her son is that it goes out
of the tribe, right? So if she passes it on to her
daughter it's less it's less disruptive, right? Because of it's less right
because you know who knows? I mean it's a potentially disruptive but
anyway it's just pushing it off. It's not immediately a problem.
If the daughter marries someone from the mother's original tribe.
In theory and still right. So obviously the highest likelihood is it
will pass out, but at least it's not immediately disruptive. Okay. So
anyway, היך בת ירשת שני מטות? Heich bat yoreshet shnei matot? אלא
זו ש... Ela zo she... we just said that and ואין לי
אלא בת. ve-ein li ela bat. I only know a daughter inherits
from her mother. בן מנין? ben minayin? How do I know a
son inherits from her mother? And then it would immediately pass from
one tribe to the next. אמרת קל וחומר. amarta kal vachomer. ומה
בת שהורע כחה בנכסי האב יפה כחה בנכסי האם. uma bat she-hura
kochah b'nichsei ha-av yafe kochah b'nichsei ha-em. A daughter whose power is
weak by the father's property, weaker, that she only gets second, right?
And nevertheless her position is strong by her mother, now, meaning we
don't know, it's clear, it's clear she inherits from her mother and
she's only on second line of inheritance from the father. בן שיפה
כחו בנכסי האב, ben she-yafe kocho b'nichsei ha-av, the son who's first
in line from the father's property, אינו דין שיפה כחו בנכסי האם?
eino din she-yafe kocho b'nichsei ha-em? Isn't it clear that he also
would have a strong position in his mother's property? So if a
daughter inherits, certainly a son inherits. Now, that's fine. וממקום שבאת. u-mimakom
she-bata. Now here becomes a core question: does the order still apply
by the case of the mother's property? Okay, so that's going to
be an interesting debate. So this for now we're saying this Braita
says yes, you apply the same principles of the model you're learning
from. מה להלן בן קודם לבת, ma le-halan ben kodem le-bat, the
same way in the case of the father's inheritance the son comes
before the daughter, אף כאן, af kan, here too, בן קודם לבת,
ben kodem le-bat, the son comes before the daughter. Rabbi because, you
know, that's what we learn it from, so we apply the son
that we know by the father that inherits and then we're also
going to assume he comes first.
וממקום שבאת u-mimakom she-bata is a comment on the logic of the
argument?
Yes. You're learning out that the son inherits from the case of
inheriting the father, so just like from the case, right? Exactly, by
analogy, the same way by the father a son comes first, by
the mother as well.
I don't remember this phrase.
Okay.
רבי יוסי איצטריך ליה מדרש הלכה. Rabbi Yossi itztarich lei midrash ha-halacha.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה ורבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי אמרו Rabbi Yossi b'rabbi
Yehuda v'rabbi Elazar b'rabbi Yossi amru משום רבי זכריה בן הקצב. mishum
rabbi Zechariah ben HaKatzav. So that's a name you don't see too
much. Right, what was his father was a butcher or something. Anyway,
it was just his name, רבי זכריה בן הקצב. Rabbi Zechariah ben
HaKatzav. אחד הבן ואחד הבת שוין בנכסי האם. echad ha-ben v'echad ha-bat
shavin b'nichsei ha-em. Now, he said, you know as we're going to
see, you made it from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but a
קל וחומר kal vachomer can't exceed the case it was learning from.
דיו. dayo. So since, so since you learned the son, if the
daughter gets, certainly the son gets, fine, the son will get, but
he's not going to get more than the daughter. They divide equally.
Yes, they divide equally. You only brought in the son, yes, even
if he's older? Yes. You only brought in the son on the
basis of learning from the daughter. So therefore, he will not get
more than the daughter. The son and daughter inherit equally בנכסי האם.
b'nichsei ha-em. Okay, no. So we're going to see all that, Michael.
So anyway, so מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why? דיו לבא מן הדין
להיות כנדון. dayo la-ba min ha-din lihyot ke-nadon. It's enough for the
thing that was learned out from the derivation to be like the
thing it was learned from. So the same way the daughter—so how
do we know a son gets? By because if a daughter gets,
certainly a son gets. Fine, but that doesn't prove that he gets
more than a daughter. You can't exceed—you can make the argument that
he certainly gets, you can't make an argument that he gets more.
So the Gemara says ותנא קמא לא דריש דיו? v'tana kamma lo
darish dayo? So you're telling me the Tana Kamma who says the
son gets first, he doesn't hold of this principle of דיו dayo
that you can't exceed the thing you learned from? דדיו דאורייתא הוא.
d'dayo d'oraita hu. We know that's part of a biblical rule within
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. How do you know it? דתניא, d'tanya, there's
one of the few cases that we're set to make a claim
that some of these hermeneutic rules, you know, are directly in the
פסוק. pasuk. The rule, not the application of it. Okay. מדין קל
וחומר כיצד? m'din kal vachomer keitzad? This is, you know, from the
sort of the whole Braita of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that המדות
שהתורה נדרשת בהן. ha-middot she-ha-Torah nidreshet bahen. So how do you know
a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Where do you learn that from the
פסוקים? pesukim? ויאמר ה' אל משה ואביה ירק ירק בפניה הלא תכלם
שבעת ימים. vayomer Hashem el Moshe v'aviha yarok yarak b'faneha halo tikalem
shivat yamim. He's going to say, God says this by when Miriam
spoke לשון הרע lashon hara against Moshe. God said, and if her
father were to spit in her face, she'd be embarrassed for seven
days, at least. So now that I, the God, the שכינה Shechinah
is angry with her, she has to be shut up for seven
days outside the camp. תסגר שבעת ימים מחוץ למחנה ואחר תאסף. tisager
shivat yamim michutz lamachane v'achar t'asef. So the Gemara says okay, but
I mean if a father is seven, then when God gets angry
at her, it should be more than seven, right? קל וחומר לשכינה
ארבעה עשר. kal vachomer l'Shechinah arba'ah asar.
So you know, logically, you know, if God's angry, if a father,
you know, but due to a shame from a father it's seven
days embarrassment, shame from God should logically be more than that. Now
why did we go to fourteen? Why did we double it? So
Tosafot says well, we would know that it would be more than
seven. And once it would be more than seven, the whole idea
of like, you know, shutting somebody up outside the camp like you
have by the מצורע Metzora and so is like seven days. They
come in
seven-day units. Now Tosafot says we really would have only known seven
days and a minute, okay. You can't necessarily know double. You know
that it would be more, but once it would be more, the
units are seven-day units. Okay, so that's, I mean Tosafot's discussion why
we're saying fourteen, but that's the one that's I think the simplest
read. Anyway, so it should be more by the שכינה. Shechinah. So
why wasn't it more? אלא דיו לבא מן הדין להיות כנדון. ela
dayo la-ba min ha-din lihyot ke-nadon. So it's enough to the thing
that's learned out from the derivation to be from the source of
the derivation. So since we know that the father... seven and therefore
banishment from God is maybe has to be at least that much,
but we can't prove that it's more and we don't know how
much more, so we limit it to the basis of it. We
limit it to the seven days. So the same here. If a
daughter inherits certainly a son, can you prove that a son gets
more, that a son gets less? No. You just know that he's
certainly as much as the daughter. So therefore, so how does the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma say, why does the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
say that you have a son gets first by נכסי האם? nichsei
ha'em? One minute. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא דלרבנן בעלמא דרשא.
Ella d'l'rabbanan b'alma darsha.
You're right. Of course the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds of the
general principle of דיו. dayo. ושאני הכא דאמר קרא v'shani hacha d'amar
kra ממטות. mimatot. It says בנות בת יורשת נחלה ממטות. benot bat
yoreshet nachalah mimatot.
She inherits from tribes. And we set up the scenario, father and
mother different tribes and they both die. Okay. So since both tribes
are equated in that word מטות, matot, it suggests that the inheriting
from the father and the inheriting from the mother are the same.
So מקיש מטה האם למטה האב. makish mateh ha'em l'mateh ha'av. They're
both in that word מטות, matot, inheriting from the mother's tribe and
the father's tribe. מה מטה האב בן קודם לבת, mah mateh ha'av
ben kodem l'bat, the same way in the father's tribe the son
comes before the daughter, אף מטה האם בן קודם לבת. af mateh
ha'em ben kodem l'bat. So this פסוק pasuk will tell me that
that sense of priority, that sense of, you know, order
sequence is maintained even in the case where the mother dies. Now,
I want to just pause for a moment because the גמרא Gemara
is not over and we're actually going to see that it was
going to be a very vigorous debate, this halachic question, when a
mother dies, do sons and daughters inherit equally? Okay, there's not going
to be a rule of בכור, bechor, there's not going to be
the פי שנים, pi shenayim, whatever, we'll get to that. Okay. And
as Michael said, does it matter if you had ten sons first
or, you know, ten sons and then ten daughters, each one gets
one-twentieth? Okay, order doesn't matter, sex doesn't matter, everybody gets equally. That's
a pretty egalitarian, like you know, position and the גמרא Gemara is
going to actually, there are going to be תנאים Tannaim that hold
that. I mean, we just have already תנאים Tannaim that hold that.
So the question is, it's very actually, you know, it makes a
lot of sense based on what we've been talking about, about the
idea of the משפחת האב mishpachat ha'av and patriarchy, because when things
remain in the father's tribe, it passes from father to son or
father to a male relative. It is staying within the tribe. Right?
The idea of course is that the land stays within the father's
household and stays within the tribe, which is defined by the males.
משפחת האב, mishpachat ha'av, right? That's the tribal identity. So as long
as there is a, you know, a son before a daughter, a
brother before a sister, whatever, it's going to go to the men
first for the purpose of, that way it remains within the משפחת
האב. mishpachat ha'av. If it were to go to a woman, she'd
marry somebody else and it would go out. Okay. But so that's
when the father dies, a man dies. But when a woman dies,
the property is anyway leaving, right, her ancestral home? Like this was
a Reuvenite woman or Danite woman who married a Reuvenite, whoever is
going to get from her is going to be taking it away
from the patriarchal family. So if that's true, if it's not going
to be staying in the patriarchal family, so once you're not dealing
with that patriarchal structure and maintaining that patriarchal structure, so the girls
and the boys can inherit equally. People appreciate that? I mean, it's
a very powerful idea. It's saying it's not that, oh, boys always
have to come before girls, men always have to come before women.
It's saying in the context of, you know, the patriarchal inheritance and
keeping things within the patriarchal family because it is defined as like
Avraham, Yitzchak, and Yaakov, you know, it's sort of defined through the
men, then as long as there's a man, we're going to keep
it in that tribe. We're not going to give it to a
woman who will then take it away from the tribe. But once
it's already being taken, coming from a woman and coming already taken
away from that original family and tribe, then boys, men and women
inherit equally.
But the question would be then, if a man dies and he
has a son and a daughter and brothers, right? There's no son,
then don't give it to the daughter, give it to the brother,
that way it can stay within the same...
You're right, and that is the tremendous חידוש chiddush of בנות צלפחד
benot Tzelafchad is that number one is that women would get at
all. Right? Because you should say the logic, before בנות צלפחד, benot
Tzelafchad, the logic is you will seek out any male relative, living
male relative, before you would give it to a woman in order
to keep it within the tribe. That was the logic before בנות
צלפחד. benot Tzelafchad. That's why בנות צלפחד benot Tzelafchad were so radical
is they come in and they say right after the sons, before
you give it to a brother, right, who's a pretty close male
relative, we're going to get even though it's going to entail eventually
this land leaving the משפחת האב. mishpachat ha'av. Right? And that's as
Rebbe says, that's why the פסוק pasuk uses the word והעברתם. v'ha'avartem.
I think it's really a great פשט pshat in the פסוק. pasuk.
You're going to be transferring it out of the tribe. That's why
בנות צלפחד benot Tzelafchad were so radical.
בנות צלפחד benot Tzelafchad's point was precisely the opposite, you know, we
should inherit so that we keep it within the family.
I know, that's the irony. That's the irony. I know. That is
totally the irony. I don't know what to tell you. That is
the irony. That is a good way, that is a good way
of making an argument, like for, we, you know, sort of, you
know, people have written about this about like, you know, in general
about women in תנ"ך Tanach and the whole story with רות Ruth
or whatever, like, you know, when people are not in an empowered
positions, you have to make an argument that the people in power
can hear, you know, sort of like, so, right? So, you don't,
so, so it's a much more acceptable argument to say we need
to do this to maintain our father's, you know, name and legacy,
than just to say like, hey, we deserve it, even though it's
going to be taking, even though it's going to mean that it's
going to leave our father's household, right? But you're right, it's ironic.
So the reality is they say למה יגרע שם אבינו lama yigara
shem avinu and it'll maintain שם אבינו shem avinu for one generation,
but then it's going to ultimately, long term, it's going to יגרע
שם אבינו. yigara shem avinu. You are absolutely correct.
Because the husband inherits the wife?
He inherits from his wife if he's around first. So then the
husband first, right? So that'll also take it away. That's why we
needed a special פסוק passuk for that as well. Yes. Okay. All
right, so yeah.
So it was the rabbis who decided it was only that generation
of the sons? Yes, so they really did this shift, right?
Yeah, I mean they're saying that they're, right, they're not interpreting their
act as a rabbinic legislation, they're interpreting the verses, but it's their
interpretation that limits it to that. Right. So if they hadn't done
it, בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelafchad would have been a lot less radical
if you would have left it with the modification of their uncles.
Then everything at least would have remained within the tribe. It wouldn't
have necessarily remained within the household, but it would have remained within
the tribe. Okay. So now we have this great debate, okay, what
happens when a mother dies? Do sons and daughters inherit equally? So
the גמרא Gemara says like
this, so, רב ניסאי Rav Nisa'i סבר למיעבד עובדא כרבי זכריה בן
הקצב. savar le-mevad uvda ke-Rabbi Zechariah ben Ha-Katzav. So רב ניסאי, Rav
Nisa'i, a woman died and left over sons and daughters and she
had property, and this רב ניסאי Rav Nisa'i wanted to rule like
רבי זכריה בן הקצב Rabbi Zechariah ben Ha-Katzav and to divide equally.
אמר ליה שמואל, Amar lei Shmuel, so שמואל Shmuel said to him:
כמאן? Ke-man? כזכריה? Ke-Zechariah? Who you going like? You're ruling like this
זכריה? Zechariah? אפס זכריה, Efes Zechariah, or אפס afes זכריה, Zechariah, he's
a nothing, he's a zero, forget him.
Okay, well done, poor pedagogical move.
So, רבי טבלא Rabbi Tavla עבד עובדא כרבי זכריה בן הקצב. avad
uvda ke-Rabbi Zechariah ben Ha-Katzav. רבי טבלא Rabbi Tavla did insist to
do this, he פסקנט paskened this way. He actually gave property to
the, equally to the sons and daughters. אמר ליה רב נחמן, Amar
lei Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said: מאי האי? Mai
hai? What's going on? אמר ליה, Amar lei, דאמר רבי חיננא בר
שמיה משמיה דרב, d'amar Rabbi Chinana bar Shmaya mishmeih de-Rav, because I
actually have a tradition in the name of רב, Rav, you could
sort of say who's this זכריה Zechariah guy, but here's רב, Rav,
רב Rav פסקנ'ס paskens הלכה כרבי זכריה בן הקצב. halacha ke-Rabbi Zechariah
ben Ha-Katzav. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so he said to him: זיל להדר בך. Zil
la-hadar bakh. No, I need, you have to go and reverse yourself.
Now, it's an interesting question, when he says reverse yourself, is he
saying reverse your position, reverse your ruling, take the property out of
the hands of the people you gave it to, those women, those
girls, and give it to the sons? Or is he just saying
like, you know, reverse your general פסק psak as a, you know,
as opposed to your actual particular ruling in this case? It sounds
like, you know, I think from the context it sounds like he
actually wanted him to reverse the actual case itself. ואי לא, Ve-ei
lo, and if you don't reverse yourself, מפקינא לך רבי חיננא בר
שמיה מאוניך. mafki-na lakh Rabbi Chinana bar Shmaya me-unakh. I will pull
this רבי חיננא בר שמיה Rabbi Chinana bar Shmaya out of your
ears. So, because רבי חיננא בר שמיה Rabbi Chinana bar Shmaya said
it in the name of רב. Rav. So he basically says like,
who the heck cares? Like I'm going to just completely separate him
from you. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says what that means is I'm
going to put him in חרם. cherem. And by putting him in
חרם cherem for פסקנ'ס paskens this idea in the name of רב
Rav or whatever, then you won't be able to quote him and
rely on him. The רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says, it's he says
when it says from your ear what it means is if you
don't give that property to those sons and take it out of
those girls, I'm going to come and take it out of your
property and give it to those sons. So like pull it out
of your ear, you're going to have to pay for like this
פסק. psak. Okay, so it's quite interesting, people are really exercised over
this, you know, over the fact that there would be a possibility
that girls would inherit or, you know, women would inherit equal to
men. Yes.
I just want to make sure I understand. This is only in
the case there's no husband, right?
Because then it would go to the husband?
All of this is no husband. Yes, because then it goes to
the
sons.
Correct. This is no husband, the woman dies, it directly goes, and
it goes directly from the mother to the sons. If the woman
dies and it goes to the husband, then it becomes the husband's
property and then it follows the rules of the husband's inheritance. You
are correct. Okay.
So, רב הונא Rav Huna does it matter if the daughter is
has a husband also? Does that matter?
No. No. Yeah. Okay. רב הונא Rav Huna I mean, it won't
go to the husband eventually when she dies if the husband if
she dies before her husband.
Yeah, so she can lose it by being married she can lose
it?
Correct. I mean, the prince, the point is the husband would be,
would eat the פירות, peirot, right? As the general arrangement. She has
the title, husband eats the פירות, peirot, but she would inherit it.
Anything she brought into the marriage?
Exactly. Exactly. Anything that she owned, that she did not explicitly give
title to her husband, so she has title and the husband... Okay.
So, okay. So I'm going to pull him out of your ear.
So, where were we?
Okay. רב הונא בר חייא סבר למיעבד עובדא כרב זכריה בן הקצב,
Rav Huna Bar Chiya savar lemeivad uvda keRav Zecharia ben Hakatzav, so
this רב הונא בר חייא Rav Huna Bar Chiya wanted also פסקן
pasken this way. אמר ליה רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman, so
רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to him, מאי האי? Mai hai? What's
going on here? So again רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, it's interesting to
see who are the ones that are so opposing it. So we
have שמואל Shmuel and רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, רב נחמן Rav Nachman
twice now. What's going on? אמר ליה דאמר רב הונא אמר רב.
Amar lei de'amar Rav Huna amar Rav. Now I have not only
a tradition in the name of רב, Rav, but a tradition of
רב הונא Rav Huna in the name of רב, Rav, who's also
a great authority, רב הונא. Rav Huna. הלכה כרב זכריה בן הקצב.
Halacha keRav Zecharia ben Hakatzav. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to
him, רב נחמן Rav Nachman responded, right, to who is this? To
רב הונא בר חייא. Rav Huna Bar Chiya. אשלח ליה? Eshlach lei?
You want me to go ahead and go ahead and send a
message to רב הונא Rav Huna and ask him if he really
פסקן paskens that way? איכסיף, Ichsif, he was embarrassed. Now the רשב"ם
Rashbam says, what's going on? I mean, was he making it up?
Again, I don't know, you know, so he says no. He really
did have this tradition in the name of רב הונא, Rav Huna,
but he was afraid, you know, רב נחמן Rav Nachman was coming
on so strong that he was afraid that if רב נחמן Rav
Nachman would ask רב הונא, Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav Huna himself
might reverse himself. Okay. So, I mean, you know, it's very hard
when somebody is like really like, you know, shaming you or like
like how can you have this position, right, to hold your ground.
Okay. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to
him, or overpowering you. Anyway, השתא דלאו דחנא אפיה דרב הונא, Hashta
delav dachna apeih deRav Huna, is now, if רב הונא Rav Huna
had not been alive and he wasn't there for me to actually
be able to, you know, check your claim, איצטרומי הוה מצטמית, itztirumei
hava mitztamit, you would have opposed, you would have like argued against
me, you would have opposed my position. Okay. So again, it's a
little vague, right, because was he really not honestly reporting? I mean,
again, the רשב"ם Rashbam says he was honestly reporting this tradition of
רב הונא. Rav Huna. He was just afraid that with רב נחמן's
Rav Nachman onslaught, רב הונא Rav Huna would reverse himself. Anyway,
yeah.
Exactly. Now I do, I am wondering how much this is בבל,
Bavel, ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, because רב Rav originally came from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael women had much
much greater standing in law than in בבל. Bavel. רב נחמן Rav
Nachman is from בבל, Bavel, right? רב נחמן Rav Nachman is, yeah,
yeah. So so right. So I wonder if that might have some
influence. I don't know if all these other תנאים Tannaim who also
פסקן pasken that women, all these other positions who פסקן pasken that
women get it, also are ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but רב Rav
certainly originally comes from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. What are you asking,
Michael?
What does he say in this last line? If רב הונא Rav
Huna had died then what?
If רב הונא Rav Huna had died and he wasn't around there
for me to challenge you to tell you that I would, you
know, challenge I'm going to go ask him to verify, you would
have opposed me and you know you would have maintained your opposition
to me
unjustifiably. But now that he is alive and you're afraid that I'm
going to go check with him if he really said that, now
you're willing to concede. So it's a good thing he's around for
us to keep you honest is what he says.
And what's the word איצטרומי? itztirumei?
Like I think it means like a treifs which is like a
heel, like the common, that's the way I interpret it. Like לטריז,
latriz, you know.
Yeah. תריסין, trisin, yeah, תריסי משיה, trisi Meshia, right, shutters, exactly, rebuffed,
rows
of people.
Okay.
All right. So
okay, where are we?
ואינהו כמאן סברה? Ve'inhu keman savrah? So now, who now, it's so
funny. רב נחמן Rav Nachman who is so against, right this, right,
like who's he going like? Like they had a tradition in the
name of רב הונא Rav Huna in the name of רב, Rav,
etc. Where's his tradition that you reject this position? כי הא דרב
ושמואל, Ki ha deRav uShmuel, so he has a different tradition in
the name of רב. Rav. And not only ושמואל veShmuel we already
heard was opposed to it, but he has a tradition that both
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel were opposed to it. כי הא דרב
ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו אין הלכה כרב זכריה בן הקצב. Ki ha deRav
uShmuel de'amri tarveihu ein halacha keRav Zecharia ben Hakatzav. So שמואל Shmuel
clearly was opposed to it. רב נחמן Rav Nachman who is שמואל's
Shmuel תלמיד, talmid, right, רב נחמן Rav Nachman who was שמואל's Shmuel
תלמיד, talmid, was very, you know, they were both strongly opposed to
it and there was a debate about what was רב's Rav position
about it. All right. Now, מסתמיך ואזיל רבי ינאי. Mistamich ve'azil Rabbi
Yannai. Now we're going to have an interesting little story. רבי ינאי
Rabbi Yannai was supporting himself and going, he was blind and he
was infirm, and he was going אכתפיה דרב שמלאי. akatfeih deRav Simlai.
He was being like sort of carried on the shoulders of רב
שמלאי, Rav Simlai, שמעיה, shameih, his attendant. ואתא רבי יהודה נשיאה לאפיה.
Ve'ata Rabbi Yehuda Nesia lapeih. רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda Nesia, the
grandson of רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, not to be confused
with רבי יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. רבי יהודה נשיאה Rabbi Yehuda
Nesia was coming to greet them, or was coming opposite them. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so who was, again, רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai said
to his attendant, בר איניש דאתי
לקבלנא, Bar inish de'ati likvalana, that man that is coming to greet
us, that person that is
coming opposite us... I'm sorry, excuse me, I got that wrong. The
attendant said to רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, בר איניש דאתי לקבלנא... Bar
inish de'ati likvalana... A man is coming at us is coming to
opposite us. הוא יאה, hu yaei, he's beautiful, וגולתיה יאה, vegulosei yaei,
and his cloak is beautiful. So he just, you know, he was
just describing what was going on in the environment to this, to
רב ינאי. Rav Yanai. So כי מטא לגבי, ki mata legabei, when
they encountered רב יהודה נשיאה, Rav Yehuda Nesiah, גששה, gashasha, so רב
ינאי Rav Yanai felt his clothes because he said he has a
beautiful cloak. This is very evocative of a, you know, of יצחק
Yitzchak and יעקב Yaakov by feeling the hairy cloak. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, he said to him, דין שירי טסק. dein shirei tasak.
What do you mean it was a beautiful cloak? The thing he's
wearing is an inferior material and it would have the same halakhic
dimensions as sackcloth. What's the minimum size of a cloth that can
become טמא? tamei? So normally, if it's not sackcloth, normal fabric is
ג' טפחים shlosha tefachim by ג' טפחים, shlosha tefachim, but sackcloth, which
is inferior, you need a larger size to have significance. So he
said, you know, this is inferior material, what do you mean that
it was so beautiful? Okay, so I don't know how that's at
all relevant to this story, but I do like the idea of
feeling the cloak and identifying the person, you know, sounds like very
much יצחק Yitzchak to me. Anyway, so בעי מיניה, bei minei,
now, now רב יהודה נשיאה Rav Yehuda Nesiah asked from רב ינאי,
Rav Yanai, מניין, minayin, so he sort of let that I guess
insult just pass. So he asked from רב ינאי Rav Yanai the
following question: מניין לבן שקודם לבת בנכסי האם. minayin le'ben shekodem le'bat
benichsei ha'em.
Okay, how do you know this question we're asking, how do you
know when the mother dies, the son comes first in inheritance? אמר
ליה, amar lei, דכתיב, dechtiv, מטות, matot, the tribes, מקיש מטה האם
למטה האב. makish mateh ha'em le'mateh ha'av. מה מטה האב בן קודם
לבת, אף מטה האם בן קודם לבת, ma mateh ha'av ben kodem
lebat, af mateh ha'em ben kodem lebat, because it says tribes, so
the same way by the father's tribe the son comes first, by
the mother's tribe as well the son comes first.
Who asked the question? רב ינאי?
Rav Yanai? No, רב יהודה נשיאה Rav Yehuda Nesiah asked this to
רב ינאי Rav Yanai and רב ינאי Rav Yanai gave the answer.
רב ינאי Rav Yanai is the big תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham.
אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב יהודה נשיאה Rav Yehuda Nesiah said,
אי מה מטה האב בכור נוטל פי שנים, אף מטה האם בכור
נוטל פי שנים. ei ma mateh ha'av bechor notel pi shnayim, af
mateh ha'em bechor notel pi shnayim. Ah! Once you're going to have
the son come first, once you're taking this approach, not the egalitarian
approach that we saw
of
these other, you know, תנאים Tannaim and אמוראים, Amoraim, you're going to
say we're going to maintain son come first, so let's go the
whole way. Let's say the son gets a double portion when he
inherits from his mother. אמר ליה לשמעיה, amar lei lishmeia, so רב
ינאי Rav Yanai said to his attendant, גוד, gud, let's basically, you
know, take me away from here. לית דין צבי למילף, leit dein
tzevi lemilaf, this guy doesn't really want to learn, he just wants
to be contentious. Now it's so funny, it's a very reasonable question,
you know, but somehow it seems like he was sort of feeling
like, oh I insulted his clothes, maybe he's asking me these questions
in order to, you know, to get back at me or something.
It's very funny, this does not get like expanded upon what was
going on with the cloak and whatever, and why was that such
a bad question? So that's what the גמרא, Gemara, now the גמרא
Gemara says וטעמא מאי. veta'ama mai. So now the גמרא Gemara is
saying, okay, but what is the answer?
So רב ינאי Rav Yanai felt, oh he's a troublemaker, let's leave,
but the גמרא Gemara says it's not such a bad question, what's
the answer? If the son comes first, how do you know the
son doesn't get double? אמר אביי
קרא, amar Abaye kra, the פסוק pasuk says, בכל אשר ימצא לו.
bechol asher yimatzei lo. Now we're going to look at the פסוק
pasuk by a בכור. bechor. It says, you know, it says, כי
יש, ki yeish, מה הפסוק, mah hapasuk, בתחילה, bi'techilat, החד אהובה והחד
שנואה וילדו לו בנים האהובה והשנואה והיה בן הבכור לשניאה לא יוכל
לבכר את בן האהובה על פני בן השנואה הבכור כי את הבכור
בן השנואה יכיר לתת לו פי שנים בכל אשר ימצא לו, hachad
ahuvah vehachad snuah veyaldu lo vanim ha'ahuvah vehasnuah vehaya ben habechor lasnuah
lo yuchal levaker et ben ha'ahuvah al pnei ben hasnuah habechor ki
et habechor ben hasnuah yakir latet lo pi shnayim bechol asher yimatzei
lo, בכל אשר ימצא לו. bechol asher yimatzei lo.
So the בכור bechor gets פי שנים pi shnayim of everything that
is found belonging to him, him being the father. So we're going
to say the פי שנים pi shnayim comes when it comes from
the לו, lo, when it comes from property of the father, but
not when it comes from property of the mother. בכל אשר ימצא
לו lo. לו ולא לה. lo velo lo. ואימא, ve'eima,
so now the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
הני מילי hanei milei בכור bechor שנסא אלמנה. shenasa almanah. Maybe that's
only when a, meaning a בכור, bechor, you know, when it was
a first marriage for the man, you know, it's interesting right, by
women you have the terms like בתולה, betulah, אלמנה, almanah, גרושה. grushah.
By the man you basically, you know, have just word young or
old, right? So we use the word בחור bachur to mean it
was a first marriage. So maybe that's only when it was the
first marriage for the man and a second marriage for the woman.
Why would that matter? Because if it is because for the woman,
because then it is a בכור bechor for the father but the
child is not a בכור bechor for the mother, because the mother
was a second marriage for her and she already had children from
a previous marriage. So the גמרא Gemara is saying this פסוק pasuk
says that he only gets, this child only gets פי שנים pi
shnayim from his father's estate and not his mother's estate. But the
גמרא Gemara says well maybe that's just a case where his mother
it wasn't he wasn't
the firstborn
of. פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. But that's, so
that's, let me just state that because the גמרא's Gemara going to
say it but it's really important. So the בכור bechor for נחלה,
nachalah, like everything, is defined by the father. Okay, the firstborn for
the father. ראשית אונו, Reshit ono, we're going to say, ולא אונה.
velo ono. ראשית אונו. Reshit ono.
So if a man, so that's first, you know, in the פסוקים
pesukim right there, each wife, I mean, the פשט pshat of the
פסוקים pesukim is for each wife it was each woman's firstborn child,
but the question is who's, you know, whose first- the בכור bechor
is the man's firstborn child. So if it's the man's firstborn child
and it's a woman's second or third child from a- and it's
a different marriage of hers, it doesn't matter, that's again the patriarchy.
It goes by the man's firstborn child. That's for נחלה. nachalah. For
פטר רחם, peter rechem, right, it goes by the woman's firstborn child.
So you're going to have somebody who is חייב chayav in פדיון
הבן pidyon haben but does not get פי שנים pi shnayim for
נחלה. nachalah. And you get somebody get פי שנים pi shnayim for
נחלה, nachalah, now you can't get somebody who gets, well you can
but for a different reason, but if you're getting pi- well, you
can get somebody who gets, yes, you get somebody who is first
for פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, I'd have to think this through. Yes,
if a man, yes, yes, either way, if a man was previously
married and has had a son, and then he marries another woman
and has a son, right, so that other, that son is not
going to get his double portion, but it will get פדיון הבן.
pidyon haben. Right. Right. And the reverse. If it's a man's first
son and the woman's second son, so it's not going to be
a פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, but
it's going to be the- two different types of- exactly, exactly.
Okay, this פטר רחם peter rechem and there's like בכור. bechor. Okay,
yeah. So לו lo. ולא לה. ואימא הני מילי בחור שנשא אלמנה.
Ve-eima hanni milli bachur shenasa almanah. Yes. Wait, what? Does it matter?
It's a ח chet and a כ, chaf, like those are two
different words.
I know, בכור bechor and בכור. bechor. But בכור bechor here means,
as I said no, בכור bechor with a ח chet is when
you want to speak
about a man and speak about a first marriage, it speaks about,
it contrasts בכור bechor to אלמון. almon. When it speaks about a
woman and it wants to speak about a first or second marriage,
it usually contrasts like בתולה betulah to אלמנה almanah or to גרושה.
gerushah. But בכור bechor with a ח chet for a man means
a first marriage. בחור bachur is not necessarily a בכור. bechor. Right.
I was just saying I was pronouncing it wrong. Okay, בחור. bachur.
Okay, fine, בחור, bachur, fine, sorry.
Okay, I'll try to make
my ח chet more guttural too. Okay, sounds like... Fine, ואימא הני
מילי בחור שנשא אלמנה. ve-eima hanni milli bachur shenasa almanah. אבל בחור
שנשא בתולה, aval bachur shenasa betulah, notice again, she's a בתולה, betulah,
he's a בחור. bachur. Anyway, הכא נמי דשקיל. hacha nami d'shakil. Oh,
so maybe yes, this פסוק pasuk means that he gets the- he
only gets- he gets double from his father's estate. But maybe the
reason- and not his mother's. But maybe the reason is a case
where he's not his mother's firstborn. Maybe if he was his mother's
firstborn, he would get double from her estate as well. Okay, so
you can't prove from that פסוק pasuk that somebody does not get
double from his mother's estate. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, אמר קרא amar kra ראשית אונו. reshit ono. No,
there's another פסוק pasuk in this, it says, כי הוא ראשית אונו.
ki hu reshit ono. He is this man's first strength. ולא אונה.
velo ono. So again, that extra sense of the male pronoun, his
first strength and not her, is to underscore even if it was
her first son, you only get double portion in the father's estate,
not the mother's estate. It's proof of the father's first virility. Basically.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, ההוא מיבעי ליה לבא
אחר נפלים דליהוי בכור לנחלה hahu mibaya lei le-ba-achar nefilin delahavi bechor
lenachalah מי שלבו דוה עליו, mi shelibo davah alav, לא זה שאין
לבו דוה עליו. lo zeh she-ein libo davah alav. So here's another
difference between פטר רחם. peter rechem. If a woman miscarries and then
has a viable male child, he does not get פדיון הבן pidyon
haben because he was not פטר רחם, peter rechem, he was not
the first issue of the womb. Even a non-viable issue of the
womb makes this child not be first issue of the womb after
a certain point in pregnancy. Yes, I mean, after forty days, basically,
after a very early point, right, exactly. So there would not be,
so that would not be a פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, but for
בכור bechor it goes by the first viable son. If he was
the first viable birth and a son, he would get the בכור.
bechor. And we learn it from the word of like strength. Now,
you know, again, I don't know exactly what this דרשה drasha is
about דוה עליו, davah alav, like it seems like it's going from
either from the word, you know, the strength, so it's something viable,
but then it shifts to only a child that a person would
sort of like his heart would, you know, be anguished over if
the child did not survive. So if a child was never born
alive, was born- obviously a person feels terrible in the case of
a miscarriage, but what, what were you saying? דוה davah means to
like pain. Right. Sick, sick, sick heart, right, right. I understand. So
it's saying so we're saying from that it has to be that
the child was- the child was born viable. Somebody, a child who's
born viable. viable and then dies causes of course a lot more.
You have hopes and expectations and then you have and then there's
that profound pain, right? Obviously again, there's tremendous pain in a miscarriage
as well, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying it's of a
different quality. Okay, so again all I'm saying is that I don't
know how they get the phrase לבו דוה עליו *Libo dava alav*,
it seems to somehow be a דרש *drash* on the word אונו
*ono*. Maybe you know and I'm not exactly getting that, right? Why
didn't it say נכתביה הוא היה ראשית און *nichteviah hu haya reshit
on*, you know, and therefore it had to be a viable child.
But anyway somehow the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* ראשית אונו *reshit ono* tells
us that it goes by the so for בכור לנחלה bechor lenachala.
*bechor lenachala* goes by the first viable child, by בכור bechor פטר
רחם *bechor petter rechem* it goes by the first issue of the
womb. All right, anyway so don't we need the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
ראשית אונו *reshit ono* to tell you that הלכה halacha *halacha* and
not to tell you only the mate only from the father's estate
and not the mother's estate? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אם
כן לימא קרא *im ken leima kra*, so if that was all
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* was saying let it just say כי הוא
ראשית און *ki hu reshit on*, the first strength. Okay, and therefore
means a child born that's viable, that's the בכור bechor *bechor*. מאי
אונו *Mai ono*, his strength, what's the personal pronoun? שמע מינה תרתי
*Shema mina tarti*, to tell you both things, that the child only
gets the what do you call it, the double portion of the
father's estate not of the mother's. Oh, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says one minute, וכי תימא אימא *vechi teima eima*, maybe I can
still limit the פסוקים pesukim, *psukim*, הני מילי אלמון שנשא בתולה *hani
mili almon shenasa betula*, maybe I'll flip it. Maybe now the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* is talking about a case where the man, it's a
second... when is it that... not the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, the פסוק
pasuk: *pasuk* is talking that it is that he gets the father's,
he's the firstborn of the father and the mother, but... and therefore
and he gets the father's... wait wait wait, hold on. He the
פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* is telling you that he gets the father's double
portion not the mother's. But the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is saying maybe
the case where he doesn't get the mother's double portion is when
there's... he's only a בכור bechor *bechor* to his mother and not
a בכור bechor *bechor* to his father. Okay? So if he's only
a בכור bechor *bechor*, you know, the status of בכור bechor *bechor*
really comes by virtue of the father. So if he's only a
בכור bechor, *bechor* to his mother and not a בכור bechor *bechor*
to his father, he would not get a double portion.
אבל *Aval*, so הני מילי אלמון שנשא בתולה *hani
mili almon shenasa betula*, if it is a not a בכור *bechor*
to his father and a בכור *bechor* to his mother, so he's
not a full בכור *bechor* so he doesn't get a double portion
from his mother. But אבל *aval* let me say, בכור שנשא בתולה
*bechor shenasa betula*, if it is a first both a father's firstborn
בכור *bechor*, both a father's firstborn and a mother's firstborn, let me
say that because he has a status of firstborn by virtue of
his father and he also is
a firstborn of his mother, let him
now get a double portion from his mother. הכא נמי דשקיל *Hacha
nami dishakila*, let him get it. אלא אמר רבא ela amar Rava,
*ela amar Rava*, so רבא *Rava* says, אמר קרא לו lo. משפט
הבכורה *amar kra lo mishpat habechora*. Because to him is the משפט
הבכורה *mishpat habechora*. Now "him" here means the son, the firstborn son,
the son of the hated wife as opposed to the son of
the beloved wife. Right, that's the context of the פסוקים pesukim. *psukim*,
the "lo" refers to the son. But we're going to do the
דרשה drasha. *drasha* differently. משפט הבכורה לאיש ולא משפט הבכורה לאשה *mishpat
habechora le'ish velo mishpat habechora le'isha*. Not talking about the son but
talking about the parent. "Lo" to a male parent father is the
law of firstborn, to a female parent is not the law of
firstborn, so it only goes by the father's estate not by the
mother's. So it's pretty funny, you know רב ינאי *Rav Yannai* who
said get out of here this guy's a troublemaker, it took the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* a lot of effort to prove that you don't
get if the son comes first by the mother that he doesn't
get a double portion. So again what that underscores is is that
even when its when mothers die you're not working within the standard
sort of patriarchy, right? It's again within the patriarchy what's the idea
of a double portion? I mean what is that about? What that's
about is is that the firstborn is seen as the head of
the family and therefore right and again the male head of the
family and therefore he gets a larger stake in the estate. Okay?
So if though however that's all when you're dealing within maintaining the
father's family, but when it's coming through the mother and this is
not operating like that where he's not going to get a double
portion. Now by that same logic girls and boys shouldn't you know
men and women should inherit equally, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
saying no, even if so even though we've established that men come
even though this position very strongly holds men comes first even though
again we're not within that patriarchal construct at least you're not going
to get a double portion. That really only makes sense in that
classic patriarchal construct. That makes sense I understand. This the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is making the following assumption, this is an אלמון *almon* who
married a בתולה *betula*. Yeah. Right? So it's פדיון הבן *pidyon haben*,
it's her firstborn. Right? But it's not his firstborn. Right. Because he
had a he had a son with another woman. Right. But with
this wife he could have been a בכור לנחלה *bechor lenachala* with
this wife. Yeah what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying though so
in the general in the history of his marriages and childbirth. No,
not for for him for the mother's property it could have been
a בכור *bechor* not for his property exactly. A man can only
have one son who gets a double portion. Again, because he- not
with each wife. Correct, that's the whole point. The whole point is
you look at this as משפחת האב. mishpachat ha'av. Ignore the wives,
just look at the children. And you get the oldest son, and
that gets double portion. You don't look at them as different families,
right? That's the idea of משפחת האב. It's all one family, all
based on the father's children. So there's only one בכור לנחלה. Okay,
but the גמרא's gemara הוה אמינא hava amina was even though you've
proven that if he's a בכור to his mother, he doesn't get
a double portion, maybe that's when he's not a בכור to his
father. But if he has a status of בכור that he gets
through his father and he's a בכור to his mother, maybe he
gets a double portion from his mother? And then the גמרא rejected
that as well. No, double portion only comes from the father's estate,
not from the mother's. This only answered the question, that last question
was if he's both. If he's both, maybe can you have a
woman who has two בכור children like different men? Right, yes, correct,
correct. And then they would both get the first double portion of
their fathers. But you wouldn't know what to do with the mother
if you were saying- well, it would be her firstborn, her firstborn.
Meaning, if he's a בכור to his father and that is necessary
to give him a status of בכור, then can we piggyback on
that and say that if he's also the בכור to his mother,
he gets a double portion from his mother? And the גמרא said
no, not even that. All right, so this I think is like
a really fascinating גמרא. Once it's passing through the mother, you're no
longer operating within the, you know, patriarchal household. The, you know, the
property is taken away from the patriarchal household from the mother's tribe
and whatever. And therefore does it completely rearrange, you know, how the
distribution is? So you know, and it's very interesting how like, you
know, how passionately some, you know, rabbis, you know, argued against- against
sort of the equal division. Okay, so now the גמרא says like
this, והאיש את אשתו, veha'ish et ishto, and this is the other
place in which it goes away from the, you know, goes away
from that patriarchal structure is when a man inherits his wife. All
right, so מנא הני מילי, mana hani mili, and that was the,
you know, okay, so מנא הני מילי, mana hani mili, where do
you get this from? דתנו רבנן: detanu rabanan: שארו זו אשתו. she'ero
zo ishto. You know, it says כי אם לשארו הקרוב אליו, ki
im lishe'ero hakarov elav, you should give it to his flesh who's
close to him. So his flesh, that's his wife. Wife-centric patriarchy, in
other words, he's inheriting- it's going to the man. Yeah, but he's
taking it away from where she's from. That was the problem, בנות
צלפחד, benot tzelofchad, once they get it, if it's going to go
to their either their sons or their husbands, it's going to go
away. Right. שארו זו אשתו, she'ero zo ishto, מלמד שהבעל יורש את
אשתו, melamed shehaba'al yoresh et ishto, he inherits his wife. Now, that's
not פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk because the פסוק pasuk says
that this פסוק pasuk. is talking about who it passes to, ונתתם
את נחלתו לשארו. venatatem et nachalato lishe'ero. So it means you should
give it to his wife if we read שארו she'ero as אשתו.
ishto. So that's what the גמרא's going to ask. יכול אף היא
תירשנו, yachol af hi tirashenu, maybe she inherits from him? תלמוד לומר:
talmud lomar: וירש אותה, v'yarash otah, and he will inherit. Now the
אותה otah is את הנחלה, et hanachala, that's the feminine. But the
גמרא is learning the- reading it וירש אותה, v'yarash otah, he inherits
from her. הוא יורש אותה ואין היא יורשת אותו. hu yoresh otah
ve'ein hi yoreshet oto. So it's treating the אותה otah as his
wife, not as the נחלה. nachala. Okay, so the גמרא says, wait
a minute, האי קרא לאו הכי כתיבי. hai kra lav hachi ktivi.
That's not what the פסוק pasuk. says. The פסוק pasuk says ונתתם
את נחלתו לשארו, venatatem et nachalato lishe'ero, it says you give it
to his wife. How can you say it means that he gets
from his wife and he doesn't give it to his wife? It's
close, means man. Okay, אמר אביי תריץ הכי: amar Abaye taritz hachi:
ונתתם את נחלתו לקרוב אליו שארו וירש אותה. venatatem et nachalato l'karov
elav she'ero v'yarash otah. Okay, וירש אותה. v'yarash otah. So אותה otah
and we're saying means he inherits from her and he doesn't inherit
from him. Anyway, so Abaye says here's how you read the פסוק:
pasuk ונתתם את נחלתו לקרוב אליו, venatatem et nachalato l'karov elav, you
sort of take the ל lamed also, ונתתם את נחלתו לקרוב אליו,
venatatem et nachalato l'karov elav, and then it says as far as
שארו she'ero is concerned, as far as his wife is concerned, וירש
אותה, v'yarash otah, he's going to inherit his wife. יירש אותה. yirash
otah. יירש אותה. yirash otah. Okay, he will inherit from his wife.
Okay, so- so Rava says, אמר רבא, amar Rava, סכינא חריפא מפסקה
קראי? sakina charifa mafseka k'rai? A sharp knife is going to divide-
cut the פסוק? pasuk What are you doing? You're cutting the פסוק
pasuk out like that. Hey, where you getting your knife to cut
the פסוק pasuk in half like that? אלא אמר רבא, Rava rather
he says, הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: ונתתם נחלת שארו לו. venatatem nachalat
she'ero lo. So he's like, we can't totally reread it like that.
Okay, so what we're gonna do is we're only gonna slightly reread
it. Okay, what we're gonna do is we're gonna just- just use
two words, okay, just do two letters. He says, נחלתו לשארו, nachalato
lishe'ero, what we're gonna do is we're gonna take away the ל
lamed and we're gonna take this ו... vav... And this ו, vav,
excuse me, this ו vav and this ל, lamed, ונתתם venatatem את
et נח... Nach... or no, excuse me, this ו, vav, excuse me,
this ו vav and this ל, lamed, ונתתם venatatem את et נחלת
nachalat שארו she'ero לו. So we're not totally cutting up the פסוק.
pasuk. We're just moving two letters. Got it? ונתתם venatatem את et
נחלת nachalat שאר she'er לו. שארו she'ero לו. All right. So, so
קסבר, kasavar, he's of the opinion, גורעין gorenu מוסיפין mosifin ודורשין. vedorshin.
You take the letter away, you add the letter back, and then
you make your דרשה. drasha. Exactly. Okay. So the גמרא says, all
right, so that's a lot of cutting up a פסוק. pasuk, Wait,
so... so, but what's the legal import of this hermeneutics? Is it
אסמכתות asmachtos or it's דאורייתא? de'oraita? Okay, so thank you for asking
that. So because these דרשות drashot seem a real stretch, רמב"ם Rambam
is of the opinion that a husband inheriting from his wife is
only דרבנן. derabbanan. Almost all ראשונים Rishonim argue. רמב"ם Rambam also holds
that a כהן—this kohen week's פרשה—a parsha כהן kohen becoming טמא tameh
to his wife, which is not in the פרשה, parsha, which is
not in the פסוקים, pesukim רמב"ם Rambam says that's only דרבנן. derabbanan.
How could you דרבנן derabbanan allow an איסור issur דאורייתא? de'oraita? So
he says they made her like a מת מצווה. meit mitzvah. They
said nobody else is allowed to bury her, only the husband, so
she's a מת מצווה, meit mitzvah, so he's allowed to be מטמא
mitameh to her. But all the other ראשונים Rishonim assume that we
read this as a דאורייתא de'oraita דרשה. drasha. Now, of course, what
you might say is, one minute, this has to be that a
husband inherits from his wife in the Torah. What else would have
been the problem with בנות צלפחד? Bnot Tzelafchad? Why would the uncles
have complained? So what's the answer? Why would the uncles have complained
if there was not that it's going to take it away from
the tribe if there's not a rule that the husbands would inherit
from them? Their kids. As we've already established, as long as the
mother passes on to her children, it's going to take away from
the tribe, right? So we don't know from the בנות צלפחד Bnot
Tzelafchad story that the husband inherits the wife. You know that when
the wife inherits, it'll pass on, it can pass on to a
different man. But that different man would be—it could be her kids,
not necessarily her husband. Yes. But isn't the significance of this that
we're saying a wife doesn't inherit her husband? I mean, like... A
husband inherits from his wife, a wife does not inherit from her
husband. But that's like—meaning the fact that a husband inherits from his
wife doesn't seem radical to me, like... Right, correct. It's not radical,
but it's not in the פסוקים. pesukim And they're taking a פסוק
that a wife inherits from her husband and saying no she doesn't.
If you read—if you read this word as שארו, she'ero, פשט pshat
of the פסוקים pesukim we could say is that שארו she'ero is
like the פסוק by the—this week's פרשה parsha by the כהן. kohen.
It says, כי אם לשארו הקרוב אליו. ki im lish'ero hakarov elav.
Who is a כהן kohen מטמא mitameh to? His flesh. Who's his
flesh? לאמו ולאביו ולבנו ולבתו ולאחיו ולאחותו הבתולה הקרובה אליו. L'imo ul'aviv
ul'vno ul'vito ul'achiv ul'achoto habetulah hakerovah elav. It doesn't say his אשתו.
ishto. So you could have said שארו she'ero means his blood relative.
פשט pshat of the פסוק is his wife is not here at
all. Okay, once we read שארו she'ero as אשתו, ishto, then פשט
pshat becomes his wife inherits from him, and then we have to
completely re-read it to say he inherits from his wife. So that's
a double problem, because it probably is about blood relatives. Right, and
I want to say something. Let's say the הלכה halacha was—let's say
the הלכה was not that a husband inherits from his wife. Who
would inherit from her? Her... her father, her brother, and therefore the
property would go back to the ancestral estate. Right? So the only
time the property would go away from the ancestral estate would be
when it would pass on to her male children, which is what
we discussed earlier, okay, or female who then marry, whatever. But when
you say that now the husband inherits her, right, then you're really
ensuring that the property is going to go away from the ancestral—right,
yeah. It would also make more sense, like if a woman has
children and then her husband dies... If her husband dies and they're
young, wouldn't it go back to her? Yeah, I mean... well, you
know, the פסוקים psukim sort of talk about that, ושבה אל בית
אביה כנעוריה. veshavah el beit aviha kine'ureiha. It sounds like as long
as there are children she still stays within the husband's household, but
if she has no children and her husband dies she goes back,
at least conceptually. You know, whether practically... More likely the children will
still feel like connected to her family. Ah, in that case. Yeah,
but the פסוקים psukim make it sound like as long as there
are surviving children she sort of stays in her husband's household even
after he dies. Let's—let's just finish this one דרשה. drasha. והתנא מייתי
לה מהכא. Veha'tana meiti lah mehacha. The following תנא tanna learns out
that a husband inherits from his wife but not the reverse from
the following דרשה. דתניא: Detanya: וירש אותה. Ve'yarash otah. Forget שארו. she'ero.
That's talking about blood relatives. Okay, we're not going to play with
the שארו. she'ero. That's too complicated. We're just going to jump right
here. וירש אותה. Ve'yarash otah. Just read those two words by themselves.
He inherits from her. The man inherits from his—from his wife. Okay.
מלמד שהבעל יורש את אשתו, Milamed she'habal yoresh et ishto, דברי divrei
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי ישמעאל אומר, אינו צריך. Rabbi Yishmael omer
eino tzarich, You don't have to learn it from there. הרי הוא
אומר: Harei hu omer: וכל בת ירשת נחלה ממטות בני ישראל לאחד
ממשפחת מטה אביה תהיה לאיש לאשה. V'chol bat yoreshet nachalah mimatot bnei
Yisrael leachad mimishpachat mateh aviha tihyeh l'ish l'ishah. על אשתו של בעל
הכתוב מדבר. Al ishto shel ba'al hakasuv medaber. Right, so the פסוק
we—in the context... The פסוק in the context of בנות צלפחד Bnot
Tzelofchad is saying this woman will marry and gets an inheritance, she’ll
marry from another tribe and the and the inheritance will pass away.
So how is it going to pass off to how is it
going to go to the other tribe? It must be her husband
will inherit from her. Now as we’ve just discussed, no, not necessarily.
The way a woman’s inheritance can get away from the tribe is
not necessarily through the husband, it could be through the son. But
what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is going to do now is he’s
going to line up a whole list of פסוקים psukim that make
it clear that when a woman inherits from the נחלה nachla will
go to a different tribe. And the question is do any of
those make it clear that it goes to the husband or could
they all be interpreted that they go to the son? So let’s
just read those פסוקים and we’ll pick up with that. What? Which
goes first? There’s a husband and there’s first the husband, but we
are first establishing the husband. But yes, the husband inherits before the
son or before the children. Okay so רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael אומר
omer, אינו צריך, eino tzarich. הרי הוא אומר וכל בת יורשת נחלה
ממטות בני ישראל לאחד ממשפחת Harei hu omer vechol bat yoreshet nachala
mimtot bnei Yisrael leachad mimishpachat etcetera, ועל עסק הבעל הכתוב מדבר, ve’al
esek habaal hakatuve m’daber, right? You see? If a woman were to
marry, the property would go out of the tribe and that must
be because the husband inherits. ואמר ולא תסב נחלה לבני ישראל ממטה
אל מטה אחר. Ve’amar velo tisov nachala livnei Yisrael mimate el mate
acher. You cannot allow the inheritance to go to a different tribe,
it must be because the husband inherits. ואומר ולא תסב נחלה ממטה
למטה אחר, Ve’omer velo tisov nachala mimate lemate acher, same almost an
identical פסוק. ואומר ואלעזר בן אהרן מת ויקברו אתו בגבעת פינחס בנו.
Ve’omer ve’Elazar ben Aharon met vayikberu oto begivat Pinchas bno. אלעזר Elazar
died and they buried him in the plot in the valley of
פינחס Pinchas his son. So why was it פינחס'ס Pinchas’s valley? וכי
מנין לפינחס שלא היה לאלעזר? Vechi minayin lePinchas shelo haya leElazar? How
did פינחס Pinchas get a valley that he didn't get through אלעזר
Elazar his father? So the גמרא'ס Gemara’s going to say maybe he
bought it, but anyway, אלא מלמד שנשא פינחס אשה ומתה וירשה. ela
melamed shenasa Pinchas isha umeta v’yarsha. It must be that he had
a wife and he inherited from his wife and therefore פינחס Pinchas
had an inheritance that wasn’t coming through אלעזר Elazar his father. So
you see a husband inherits. All right now of course the point
is he could have bought it. His mother, his mother could have
passed it on to him, exactly. ואומר, Ve’omer, one last פסוק, ושגוב
הוליד את יאיר ויהיו לו עשרים ושלש ערים בארץ הגלעד. uSegev holid
et Yair v’hayu lo esrim v’shalosh arim b’eretz haGilad. יאיר Yair had
all of these cities. וכי מנין ליאיר שלא היה לשגוב? Vechi minayin
leYair shelo haya leSegev? Where did he get cities that his father
didn’t have? מלמד שנשא יאיר אשה ומתה וירשה. Melamed shenasa Yair isha
umeta v’yarsha. It must be he married a woman and he inherited
from her. So you have all these פסוקים that the נחלה nachla
can transfer, but as the גמרא'ס Gemara’s going to say they could
all be talking about going from mother to son, not from wife
to husband. So we are going to have to see how we
know that it goes from wife to husband. All right to be
continued. Question? Yes. I was wondering, רב נחמן'ס Rav Nachman’s a Babylonian
אמורא, Amora, and I was wondering
how his position might have related to his
position.